If they worked hard, at least they worked for themselves.
No creature among them went upon two legs.
No creature called any other creature master.
All animals were equal.
One day in early summer, Squealer ordered the sheep to follow him and led
them out to a piece of waste ground at the other end of the farm, which had
become overgrown with birch saplings.
The sheep spent the whole day there browsing at the leaves under Squealer's supervision.
In the evening, he returned to the farmhouse himself, but as it was warm
weather, told the sheep to stay where they were.
It ended by their remaining there for a whole week, during which time the other
animals saw nothing of them.
Squealer was with them for the greater part of every day.
He was, he said, teaching them to sing a new song for which privacy was needed.
It was just after the sheep had returned on a pleasant evening when the animals
had finished work and were making their way back to the farm buildings,
that the terrified neighing of a horse sounded from the yard.
Startled, the animals stopped in their tracks.
It was Clover's voice.
She neighed again, and all the animals broke into a gallop and rushed into the yard.
Then, they saw what Clover had seen.
It was a pig walking on his hind legs.
Yes, it was Squealer.
A little awkwardly, as though not quite used to supporting his considerable bulk
in that position, but with perfect balance, he was strolling across the yard.
And a moment later, out from the door of the farmhouse came a long file of pigs,
all walking on their hind legs.
Some did it better than others. One or two were even a trifle unsteady and
looked as though they would have liked the support of a stick, but every one of
them made his way right round the yard successfully.
And finally, there was a tremendous baying of dogs and a shrill crowing from
the black cockerel, and out came Napoleon himself, majestically upright,
casting haughty glances from side to side, and with his dogs gambling round him.
He carried a whip in his trotter.
There was a deadly silence.
Amazed, terrified, huddling together, the animals watched the long line of
pigs march slowly round the yard.
It was as though the world had turned upside down.
Then there came a moment when the first shock had worn off, and when, in spite
of everything, in spite of their terror of the dogs and of the habit developed
through long years of never complaining, never criticizing, no matter what happened,
They might have uttered some word of protest.
But just at that moment, as though at a signal, all the sheep burst out into a
tremendous bleating of "Four legs good, two legs better.
Four legs good, two legs better.
Four legs good, two legs better."
It went on for 5 minutes without stopping.
And by the time the sheep had quieted down, the chance to utter any protest had passed.
For the pigs had marched back into the farmhouse.
Benjamin felt a nose nuzzling at his shoulder.
He looked round.
It was Clover.